Meteor showers are incredible from the middle of the desert.
りゅうせいぐん
こういうところで見る流星群って
やっぱりすごいな｡
Yeah, it's... Well, you know?
(北村)うん 何かこう アレよね！
すごく え～っと…｡
Yes, it's very, um...
さが
(ｱﾏﾝﾃｨ)ウフフ… 言葉を捜すのが
もどかしいですね｡
It's very difficult to describe.
Yeah, no kidding.
にった
(新田)ああ まったくだ｡
なんば　むった
(南波六太)あ～ ウホン ウホン
まあ こういうのは➡
Well, it's like you're part of—
うちゅう
アレだよね 自分が宇宙に…｡
わかった！僕が感じたのはね➡
I know! I was going to say
こうして ここで見上げてるとさ
星空に吸い込まれて➡
that when I look at the sky,
it feels like the stars are sucking me in,
宇宙と一体になり 自分も宇宙の
一部だって実感できたような…➡
and I'm part of the universe...
Maybe that's what we're all feeling?
もしかしたら
みんなも同じ思いを…｡
Yes, that's what I wanted to say.
そう！私もそう言いたくて…｡
うん それそれ！宇宙の一部！
Yep, that's it...
Part of the universe!
Damn you, Kenji...
《チェッ ケンジめ～➡
I was about to say that...
おれ
俺の言おうと思ったことを…》
あれっ？おっ!?
南波さん 南波さん｡
南波さんも さっき同じ事を➡
Nanba, Nanba.
Were you about to say the same—
言おうと…アレ～!?
おお～！スッゲェ～！
Huh?
Whoa! Wow!
こんばんは～…って
やっぱアメリカだから➡
Good evening.
Wait, since we're in America, do I have to use English?
英語じゃねえと通じねえかな｡
どうしたの？ムッ君｡
What is it, Mu?
のぞ
みんな！ちょっと覗いてみなよ｡
Hey, take a look at this.
Oh, a frog!
(せりか･北村)お～っ カエルだ！
たしかコーチスキアシガエルって
言ったかな｡
I think this is a Couch's spadefood toad.
So they can live in the desert...
さばく
くわ
砂漠にもいるんだね｡
詳しいな 南波｡
You're pretty knowledgeable about this.
フッフッ…まぁな｡
｢生き物しらべ｣にハマっててさ｡
I guess.
Hibito and I were pretty hooked on observing wildlife,
ひびと
日々人と２人で 子どもの頃に…｡
back when we were kids.
＜そう 2006年７月９日
俺たち兄弟は…＞
Yes,
on July 9th, 2006,
the two of us...
ちょうさ
俺は 前回より先を調査する｡
りょうかい
(南波日々人)了解｡
I'm going to explore farther than last time.
Roger.
つね
＜兄とは 常に弟の先を
行ってなければならない｡➡
A big brother should always stay ahead of his little brother.
That is his duty for having been born earlier.
つと
それが兄としての務め＞
フフッ ヘヘッ…ヘヘッ…｡
あっ あら？どっちへ
行くんだっけ？エヘヘッ！
Huh?
Which way should I go?
July 9th, 10:01 PM.
７月９日２２時１分➡
Discovered a Japanese tree frog in the thicket behind Bamboo Newtown.
うら
しげ
竹の子ニュータウン裏の茂みにて
ニホンアマガエル｡
つぎだがわちゅうりゅう
２２時０３分 次田川中流｡
10:03 PM, Tsugida, mid-stream.
Mu!
ムッちゃぁ～ん‼
Mu, over here! Quick!
ムッちゃん こっち来いよ！早く！
What?
早く来いってば！ムッちゃん！
なぁに～？
Hurry up, Mu!
What is it?
You're so slow...
おそ
遅いよ もう‼
うわぁ！
Whoa!
Hey, Hibi... Hibito!
こ こら！日々人！こら！
Stop this!
はなして～！
P-Put me down...
ぶへっ！
おろして｡
Put me down.
Hibito! Come on...
日々人 お前な～！あ？
Huh?
うっうっ 何あれ!?
What's that?
わかんない…｡
No idea.
Oh... What's it doing?
うわあ！なんだよ｡
ハアッ｡
I-It went t-to the moon?
つ 月…行った？
SPACE BROTHERS
You've always been in my heart
But you don't say a thing or even smile
We've always been together
We're ignorant, but we believe
All the time I spent with you
Felt like a dream
We connected the stars and drew pictures
To our hearts' content
Let our hearts, shivering in excitement,
Use the sky as a canvas
And merge to form an everlasting image
#52 A Big Brother Should Always...
＜2025年の５月＞
In May of 2025...
(男性記者)では南波日々人さん➡
So, Nanba Hibito,
げつめんちゃくりくしゃ
日本人初の月面着陸者になる
ことをどう思われますか？
how does it feel, becoming the first Japanese person to set foot on the moon?
日本人にとって
月は昔から特別な存在です｡
The moon has always held special meaning for the Japanese.
そこへ国を代表して行けることは
とても光栄です｡ですが…｡
I am honored to serve as my country's ambassador to the moon.
However...
僕より先に月面を
踏むはずだった人が➡
There was someone who was supposed to step upon the moon before me,
今 この場にいないのは
残念です｡
and it's unfortunate that he couldn't be here right now.
＜晴れて月へ行くことが決まった
弟･日々人が➡
My little brother was headed to the moon.
While Hibito was holding a press conference,
栄光の記者会見をしている頃…＞
行ってきます！
Wish me luck!
＜わたくし 南波六太は
晴れて自動車会社を➡
I, Nanba Mutta,
was looking for a job after being fired by the automobile manufacturer I worked for.
しょくさが
リストラされ 職探しの真っ最中＞
＜我が弟のことを悪く
言いやがった上司に私は➡
After my supervisor insulted my brother...
やってしまった＞
ジダ～ン｡
Zidane!
I couldn't help myself.
Naturally, I was fired immediately.
たいじょう
＜もちろん一発退場＞
づつ
＜私が頭突きをした
えら
はか
お偉いさんの計らいで➡
The bigwig I'd headbutted had spread the word,
他社の他社まで
あくひょう
私の悪評は広まっていた＞
so I was blacklisted at all the other companies.
＜私は二度と 自動車開発業界には
戻れそうにない＞
I doubt I'll ever work for an auto company again.
Man...
《あ～あ…なんだかもう
どうでもよくなってきた…》
I'm starting to not even care anymore.
《日々人…
ゆめ
かな
お前は夢を叶えたんだな》
Hibito,
you've fulfilled your dream...
がふっ！
《兄とは 常に弟の先を
行ってなければならない》
A big brother should always stay ahead of his little brother.
But somehow,
《だけど…何をやっても
俺を追い越し 先を行くのは➡
my little brother, Hibito, always ends up ahead of me!
弟 日々人じゃないか！》
《俺は…ん？》
What...
《俺は今まで…
何がやりたかったんだろうか》
What have I been doing with my life?
えっ!?それ どういうこと？
ムッちゃん そっちに帰ってんの？
Huh?
What do you mean?
Mu's home?
やくいん
そうなの！役員さんに頭突きして
クビになったの あの子｡
That's right!
He headbutted his superior, and got himself fired.
Isn't that hilarious?
面白いでしょう｡
☎頭突き!?どうして？
Headbutted? Why?
さあねえ｡あの子 そういう事
聞いても言わないでしょ｡だから➡
Beats me...
He never talks to us about that stuff.
That's why...
ないしょ
あっ！これ内緒の話だったんだ｡
Oh, I was supposed to keep it secret.
☎(母)日々人には言うなって
くちど
口止めされてたの｡➡
He told me not to tell you...
あ～ あたし うっかりだわ～！
Oops, I forgot!
Really...
そうか…｡じゃあ今
ムッちゃんは？
しゅうしょくかつどう
☎(母)就職活動！
Then, what's Mu doing now?
Job hunting.
He's looking for work?
仕事探しをしてんだな？
おうえん
☎(母)そうなのよ｡応援してやって｡
That's right! Cheer him on!
Mom...
母さん…ムッちゃんのためにさ
ちょっと手伝ってくれよ｡
I need you to help me with something. For Mu.
た～いま…｡
I'm home.
Welcome home!
(母)おけ～りぃ｡
Mohri...
もうり
《毛利さん…》
《あの時…》
At that moment...
⦅うっ！あっ！ちょっと…⦆
⦅は？…ああっ‼⦆
＜あの時 毛利さんは 私達の背に
手を添えてくれていた＞
At that moment, when Mohri placed his hands on our backs...
＜まるで力をくれるように＞
As if he were giving us a push...
＜私達兄弟は その時
ちが
同じ事を思ったに違いない＞
At that moment, we brothers had the same thought.
We would go into space, the way he had.
＜この人が見てきた宇宙へ
自分も行くんだと＞
Mohri, Hibito actually did it.
毛利さん 日々人がやりましたよ｡
あいつは月へ行きます｡
He's going to the moon.
《ちなみに僕は…もうダメです》
But I'm all washed up...
《ごきげんよう》
Good night.
Hello? This is Nanba.
はい 南波でございます｡
あれ？
Huh?
《あ メールか｡
…日々人？》
An e-mail?
Hibito?
Where did I put it?
どこ置いたっけ？
Mu, are you okay?
Mom told me that you lost your job.
If you haven't found a new job yet,
you should listen to the tape you recorded on July 9, 2006.
あ～ これか？
…これだ｡
Oh, is this it?
It is.
2006...
２００６年…｡
７月９日｡
July 9.
《何で 今頃このテープを？》
Why would he want me to listen to it now?
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]裏の茂みにて
ニホンアマガエル…｡
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ](ゲコゲコゲコ…)
Discovered a Japanese tree frog in the thicket behind Bamboo Newtown.
Mu!
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]ムッちゃ～ん！ムッちゃん
こっち来いよ！早く‼
Mu, over here! Quick!
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]なぁに～？
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]遅いよ もう‼
What is it?
You're so slow...
Whoa!
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]うわぁ！
こ こら！日々人！こら！
Hey, Hibi...
Hibito! Stop this!
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]うっうっ 何あれ？
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]わかんない｡
What's that?
No idea.
This is when the UFO showed up.
《ここでＵＦＯが…》
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ](ザザザザザ…)
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ](ピィィィ…)
I don't remember any static.
《こんな音 あの時は…！》
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ](ピィィィ…)
Oh...
《おお…マジかよ!?》
Seriously?
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ](ピィィィ…)
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ](ザザザザザ…)
I-It went t-to the moon?
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]月…行った？
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]ムッちゃん 俺 今なんとなく➡
Mu, I really think...
なんとなく
しょうらい
ひこうし
将来は宇宙飛行士になってさ➡
I really think I want to become an astronaut.
I believe I can make it to the moon.
月に行くような気がしたよ｡
《先に言われた！》
H-He beat me to it!
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]ムッちゃんは どうすんだ？
What about you, Mu?
Huh? Me?
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]え？俺？
I-I...
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]お 俺は…俺は…｡
I...
《俺は 何て言った？》
What did I say?
If you're going to the moon,
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]お前が月に行くんなら➡
then I'll stay one step ahead.
兄ちゃんは
その先に行くに決まってる｡
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]俺は…➡
I'm...
火星に行くよ！
going to Mars.
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]じゃあ 約束な｡
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]お…おお 約束だ｡
Then it's a promise.
Y-Yeah... A promise.
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]俺らは２人で
宇宙飛行士になるぞ｡
[ﾃｰﾌﾟ]うん｡
The two of us will become astronauts.
Yep.
約束…｡
A promise...
《日々人が俺に
聞かせたかったのは ここか…》
That was what Hibito wanted me to hear.
Are you telling me to keep my promise,
《俺に この約束を果たせって
言ってるのか？日々人》
Hibito?
え～！１万だと!?ふざけるな！
べんとう
ちょっと弁当買ってた➡
T-Ten thousand?!
That's absurd!
I was only gone ten minutes, just to buy some lunch!
ばっきん
１０分か そこらだろ！それで罰金
１万ってどういう計算してんだよ！
How does that warrant a ten-thousand yen fine?
Don't just stand there! Say something, shaggy!
だま
黙ってね～で 何とか言ってみろ
お前！モジャモジャ！
イヤあの…１万５千円です｡
≪うるさ～い！黙れ‼≫
Uh, actually,
it's fifteen thousand yen.
Quiet! Shut up!
I won't pay ten or fifteen thousand!
１万だろうが
１万５千円だろうが➡
はら
そんな金を払う いわれは
ないんだよ！
Look at all the spaces!
大体こんな広い道路なんだ｡
ひにく
《ははっ 皮肉なもんだぜ》
Heh, the irony.
I'm hardly blocking traffic parking here for a minute!
いはんしゃ
せっけい
《この違反車も俺の設計｡
かわいそうになぁ》
I designed this car, too.
That shaggy haired guy probably blocks more traffic than I do!
Poor thing...
Are you listening to me, shaggy?
聞いてるのか モジャモジャ！
《早く帰って
読みかけの本を読みたい｡➡
I want to go home and finish reading my book.
And though it wasn't meant to be...
かな
叶わぬ夢とは わかってるけど…》
《あ～あ また昔のように
もうそう
ひた
宇宙の妄想に浸りたい》
Man...
I want to go back to dreaming about space.
Tokyo Metropolitan Area
High-West, Low-East City
Bamboo Newtown
Mr. Nanba Mutta
俺に？
To me?
ジャクサ
ＪＡＸＡ…｡
JAXA?
Why would JAXA send me something?
なんでＪＡＸＡが俺あてに？
The New Astronaut Selection
Examination
"The New Astronaut Selection Exam"?
しんき
せんばつしけん
新規宇宙飛行士選抜試験｡
しょるいせんこう
つうか
え…？書類選考を通過｡
Huh?
Your application has been accepted.
"Your application has been accepted..."
りれきしょ
私が出したのよ あんたの履歴書｡
I sent them your resume.
＜私はこの時
どんな顔をしていたのか➡
I don't remember
what expression I had on my face.
おぼ
はっきりとは憶えていない＞
さいだいげん
＜だが おそらく最大限に
しわくちゃな感じで➡
But it was probably all scrunched up,
as I wept and smiled...
泣いていたような
笑っていたような＞
(南波父)おい 六太｡帰ってんなら
あか
灯りぐらいつけろ｡
Hey, Mutta.
If you're home, you should turn on the lights.
しどう
じゃあヒビト 訓練を始めよう｡
Okay, Hibito...
We'll commence training.
Okay.
ＯＫ！早く来いよ ムッちゃん｡
Come soon, Mu.
久しぶりだなぁ
ぼうえんきょう
シャロン望遠鏡｡
It's been forever since I used the Sharon Telescope.
Wow!
あなたが来るって言うから
合わせといたのよ｡
I heard you were coming, so I lined it up.
おばちゃん｡
いらっしゃい ムッタ｡
Aunt Sharon.
Welcome, Mutta.
ないしょ
うちの母ちゃんがね 俺に内緒で
ＪＡＸＡに履歴書 送ったんだ｡
My mom sent JAXA my resume without telling me.
日々人に言われた
みたいなんだけど…｡
I guess Hibito asked her to do it.
書類選考通ったの1225人中ね
315人だって｡
Out of 1,225 applicants, 315 were accepted.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)すごいじゃない！
それに通るなんて｡
Then you did well to pass.
いや…俺は
何もしてないんだけどね｡
Nah, I didn't do anything.
ムッタの実力なら通るって
わかってたのね ヒビトは｡
Hibito must have known you were qualified.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)じゃあ 次は一次審査か｡
ひっき
難しい筆記試験ね｡
Next up is the first exam,
a very difficult written test.
受けないんだよ｡
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)どうして？
I won't take it.
Why not?
A little shake, and it all falls off.
こう…サラサラーっとね
ふるい落とされるって｡
残りの３１５人中から
２人か３人だよ｡
Only two or three of the remaining three hundred and fifteen can become astronauts.
宇宙飛行士になれんのって｡
無理だよ｡
It's impossible.
久しぶりに
セッションしてみようか｡
Want to play some music?
え～ もう忘れちゃったよ～｡
I've already forgotten how...
Huh?
ねえ ムッタ
ここにトランペットがあります｡➡
Say, Mutta...
I have a trumpet here.
たいこ
ピアノもあります｡ギターも太鼓も
ハーモニカもあります｡
I also have a piano.
As well as a guitar and drum. I even have a harmonica.
どれをやってみたい？
Which would you like to play?
⦅全部！⦆
All of them!
Oh? You're going to play all of them?
⦅ええっ！全部やるの？⦆
⦅だって 全部やってみなけりゃ
決められない⦆
Well, I can't decide until I've tried them all.
昔 ムッタにそう訊いたら
全部！って言って➡
Remember when I asked the same question when you were little?
And you tried out every single instrument?
ぱし
片っ端から音を鳴らしていったの
覚えている？
１時間かけて｡➡
For a whole hour.
それであなた その中で
トランペットを選んだのよ｡➡
You ended up choosing the trumpet.
どうして？って訊いたら…｡
When I asked you why...
⦅この中で一番 音が出にくい⦆
Because it's the hardest to play.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)昔のあなたって
そんな子だったのよ｡➡
That's how you used to be.
ちょうせん
なんにでも どんどん挑戦して
むずか
えら
難しいこと選んだ｡
You were always tackling the biggest challenges you could find.
そ そうだったかなぁ｡
トランペットを選んだのは➡
Are you sure about that?
I have a feeling I chose the trumpet because it was shiny.
単に一番
金ピカだったからじゃないかな？
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)それなら それでいいのよ｡
That's fine, too.
今のあなたにとって
一番金ピカなことは何？
Right now, what do you consider to be your shining star?
今の俺にとって…？
Right now?
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)まずは 音を出して｡➡
You need to try making noise first.
音出さなきゃ
音楽は始まらないのよ｡
You have to make noise before you can make music.
《始まらない…》
Before I can make music...
《俺にとって 金ピカなこと…》
My shining star...
⦅おばちゃん 俺さあ➡
Aunt Sharon.
You know...
日々人には 火星行くとか
言っちゃったけど➡
I told Hibito that I would go to Mars,
やっぱり まずは
月に行きたいんだよね｡➡
but I'd like to go to the moon first...
だって 月に望遠鏡 建てたら➡
You said that if we put a telescope on the moon, we could see farther into space, right?
はる
そうだい
ここからより遥かに壮大な宇宙が
見えるって言ってたよね⦆
⦅うん 言ったね⦆
I did.
⦅月に行くために
宇宙飛行士になるよ｡➡
I'll become an astronaut, so I can go to the moon.
えいご
英語は おばちゃんに
教わってるから➡
You've been teaching me English,
かがくけい
あとは 自然科学系の大学を出て➡
so I just need to major in the sciences and get a doctorate.
はくしごう
博士号を取ったりすれば
いいらしいんだ⦆
⦅そこまで調べたの｡なんだか
急にやる気になったわね⦆
You've already done your research.
Sounds like you're serious about this.
⦅これだけは
日々人に負けたくないからね⦆
I can't let Hibito beat me there.
⦅日々人より先に月に行って
シャロン望遠鏡を建てるよ！⦆
I will reach the moon before Hibito.
And I'll build the Sharon Telescope!
⦅わかった 楽しみにしてる⦆
I understand.
I can't wait to see it happen.
《忘れたふりを
続けていたせいか➡
I spent so much time pretending to forget my dream,
本当に自分の大事な気持ちを
忘れていた》
I actually did forget it.
《シャロンと話してよかった｡
シャロンおばちゃん 俺は…》
I'm glad I was able to speak with Sharon.
Aunt Sharon, I...
《俺は 宇宙へ行きたい！》
I want to go to space!
＜書類選考を通ってから１か月➡
A month after my application was accepted,
First Exam Hall
Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency
あっという間に
筆記試験の日が来た｡➡
it was time for the first exam.
じゅけんしゃ
受験者は３００人以上｡➡
Over three hundred take the exam.
この中から宇宙飛行士に
選ばれるのは ほんの２～３人｡➡
Only two or three would become astronauts...
ははっ 子どもの時から
シャロンおばちゃんのもとで➡
I learned English from Aunt Sharon when I was a kid.
英語を学んだ私に
これしきの英語問題など…＞
They can't stump me...
かいはつ
《あ…｡宇宙開発の
｢う｣の字もない｡➡
None of these words has anything to do with space!
いっぱんじょうしき
一般常識問題ばかりで来るか
ＪＡＸＡ！完全に山ハズした！》
JAXA's testing us on ordinary vocabulary?!
I completely gambled wrong.
じょい
(女医)い～い？
もちろんです｡
Are you ready?
O-Of course.
チクッとしますよ！チクッ｡
はぁ～ん｡
This will sting.
Sting.
二次試験に進めますように｡
Please let me make it to the second exam!
《私は宇宙へ行きたい｡➡
I want to go to space.
その一心だけで
のぞ
試験に臨んだわけだが…》
That's all that's driving me now.
[TV]出た！牛肉72.5％使用｡
新発売…｡
Here it is! 72.5% beef...
The new Bon Curry!
[TV]マサオも頑張れよ！
[TV]うん！
Keep at it, Masao.
た～いま｡
おけ～り｡
I'm home.
Welcome home!
こんばん
今晩 何？
ボンカリー｡
What's for dinner?
Bon Curry.
うわぁ～ ミスった！
昼もカレーだったよ｡
Eesh, I screwed up!
I had curry for lunch.
大丈夫！
｢ボンカリーうどん｣だから｡➡
Don't worry... It's Bon Curry Udon.
あ そうだ ムッちゃん
ＪＡＸＡから何か来てたよ～｡➡
Oh, that's right, Mu.
There's something from JAXA for you.
つうち
合格通知？
うわっ とっと…｡
Maybe you passed?
母ちゃん まず それ言えよ！
ボンカリーより｡
Mom!
You should've mentioned that before talking about the Bon Curry!
ははは…おぉ…｡
どうだった？
Well?
あ～らら｡
Oh!
ちょっと！どこ行くの 六太！
Hey!
Where are you going, Mutta?
ついでに 牛乳買ってきて！
ていしぼう
低脂肪！
Buy some milk on your way back!
Skim!
Wow.
《すげえ！すげえ！すげえ‼》
Wow...
Wow!
待って～！痛っ！
Wait for me!
Hey, stop crying!
うわっ！ケーキ買ってこなきゃ｡
Oh, I have to buy a cake!
なんの曲？
さあ？
What song is that?
Beats me.
起きろって！ほらっ！
行くぞ！
Get up!
Come on!
Pull it together.
Let's go!
かな
＜メロディなきメロディを奏で➡
I play a tune with no melody,
道なき道へ行こう＞
and walk where there is no road.
＜そこに 俺にとって一番の➡
This will take me
金ピカがあるのだ＞
to my shining star!
現在
あっ‼南波さん！カエルが
逃げちゃい…あれ？
Oh!
Nanba, the frog's running away...
Huh?
オホン！みんな見ろよ！
Check it out, guys!
のぼ
いい月が昇って来てるぜ～｡
The moon is spectacular.
大声出したら 月の日々人に➡
Looks close enough that if I yell loud enough, Hibito might hear me.
聞こえるんじゃね～か
っつ～くらい 近くに見えんな｡
フフフ…ヒッ ヘッ ヘクション！
As you place your hopes on the distant moon
And leave on your journey
You smile in spite of your loneliness
Because you believe in yourself
It doesn't matter if your wings don't match
Spread them out
As you
begin your long journey (try now) (try now)
I'm sure you can make it
Please don't hesitate
to move straight forward
You took
all your pain and sorrow (no more) (no more)
And turned it into your strength
So I'm sure even your destiny to fight many a battle
Is on your side
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#53 Stand on the Moon Together Alive
It's only been two months since I landed on the moon.
＜俺が月に来たのは
たった２か月前＞
＜でも もっと長い間
いる気がするんだよな＞
But it feels like I've been here much longer...
Probably because of the accident.
＜やっぱり あの事故のせいか？＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Stand on the Moon Together Alive"
＜ムッちゃんに 感謝しねえとな＞
I should thank Mu.